Dr Melinos Averkiou

CURRICULUM VITAE

CONTACT CYENS Centre of Excellence Email: m.averkiou@cyens.org.cy

Information Dimarchias Square 23 Phone: +357-99887483

Nicosia 1016 Web: https://melinos.github.io

Cyprus Google Scholar Profile: https://goo.gl/iXtTsn

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research lies in artificial intelligence, specifically at the intersection of machine learning and computer vision, with a focus on discriminative and generative deep neural models for 3D vision. In my view, achieving strong AI is closely linked to making real and virtual worlds indistinguishable. The primary goal of my work is therefore to bridge their gap, to the point where the virtual becomes seamlessly integrated with the real. To achieve this, I develop novel methods aimed at both understanding real-world environments and generating virtual environments across multiple scales, from objects to buildings and entire cities. My work enables AI tools advancing not only engineering, robotics, and extended reality, but also revolutionizing areas like autonomous systems, urban planning, remote sensing, and healthcare.

EDUCATION University College London, London, UK

10/2011 - 09/2015

Department of Computer Science

PhD in Computer Science

Thesis: Data-driven Modelling of Shape Structure

Advisor: Prof. Niloy Mitra

Stanford University, Palo Alto, USA

08/2014 - 09/2014

Geometric Computing Group

Visiting PhD student

Advisors: Prof. Leonidas Guibas & Dr Vladimir Kim

University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK

10/2009 - 10/2010

Computer Laboratory

MPhil in Advanced Computer Science (GPA: 75/100)

Thesis: 3D Interfaces for 3D Modelling

Advisor: Prof. Neil Dodgson

University of Cyprus, Nicosia, Cyprus

09/2005 - 06/2009

Department of Computer Science

BSc in Computer Science (GPA: 9.3/10), summa cum laude - top of the class

Thesis: A multi-touch interface for 3D navigation inside the virtual world of a museum exhibit

Advisor: Prof. Yiorgos Chrysanthou

PROFESSIONAL CYENS Centre of Excellence, Nicosia, Cyprus

07/2019 - present

Experience

Research Department

Associate Professor (Research)

Group leader of the Visual Computing Group (VCG), working on making real and virtual worlds indistinguishable, contributing to the progression towards strong AI. Results published in top venues including ICCV, 3DV, WACV, SGP. In charge of the organization's AI infrastructure, including Prometheus, the first peta-scale supercomputer in Cyprus dedicated to AI.

MindXs Ltd, Nicosia, Cyprus

03/2021 - present

Co-founder

Director of the R&D effort on artificial intelligence for automating electroencephalogram (EEG) signal processing for diagnostic purposes. In charge of CerebroEEG, the company's automated EEG analysis web platform. Responsible for raising funding, secured €100k pre-seed funding, applied for €500k seed funding.

University of Cyprus, Nicosia, Cyprus

07/2019 - present

Department of Computer Science

Adjunct Research Scientist

Principal investigator for the ANNFASS project (2018–2021), funded by the Cyprus Research & Innovation Foundation with € 250k. ANNFASS is the first neural network framework for understanding the structure and style of historical buildings.

Course instructor for Deep Learning (DSC515), Computer Vision (CS447), Computer Vision (Master in AI – MAI644).

University of Cyprus, Nicosia, Cyprus

10/2015 - 06/2019

Department of Computer Science

Research Scientist

Post-doctoral research fellow, working on deep learning for 3D vision, funded by a UCY Post-Doctoral Fellowship with €44k. Results published in CVPR (424 citations to date), the highest impact scientific conference according to Google Scholar.

Course instructor for Visual Computing (CS607), Computer Games Engineering (CS653), Programming Problem Solving Methods (CS032).

Shenzhen Institutes of Advanced Technology, Shenzhen, China

10/2015 & 01/2016

Visual Computing Research Center

Visiting Research Scientist

Post-doctoral visitor, collaborating with local researchers on representation learning for shape analysis. Results published in ACM TOG, the top computer graphics journal (impact factor 6.2).

Grants

- Cyprus Research & Innovation Foundation *Infrastructures* Grant − €75.000 2024 − present Co-principal Investigator for CRAFTC Project.
- Horizon Europe *CL2-2021-HERITAGE-01-04* Grant − € 600.000 2022 − present Co-principal Investigator for PREMIERE Project.
- CYENS Centre of Excellence Internal Research Grant € 50.000 2022 2023 Principal Investigator for DeepRecNet Project.
- Cyprus Research & Innovation Foundation *PRE-SEED* Grant − € 100.000 2021 − 2022 Principal Investigator for MindXs project.
- CYENS Centre of Excellence Starting Grant € 190.000 2019 2022 Principal Investigator for VCG Group.
- Cyprus Research & Innovation Foundation EXCELLENCE Grant € 250.000 2018 2021
 Principal Investigator for ANNFASS Project.

	• NVIDIA GPU Grant – €2.500 & €1.500 Principal Investigator	2017 & 2018
Fellowships &	 University of Cyprus Post-Doctoral Fellowship – € 44.000 	2016 – 2018
Scholarships	 University College London Studentship Award (Funded by EPSRC) – £86.0 	2011 – 2015
	• Rabin Ezra Scholarship Trust Bursary – £5.000	2014
	• Cyprus State Scholarship Foundation PhD Scholarship – € 15.000	2011 – 2014
	• A.G. Leventis Foundation – PhD Scholarship £5.000	2011 – 2012
	• University of Cambridge Studentship Award (Funded by EPSRC) – £15.500	0 2009 – 2010
	• Cyprus State Scholarship Foundation MSc Scholarship – € 5.000	2009 – 2010
	• A.G. Leventis Foundation MSc Scholarship – £5.000	2009 – 2010
	• Darwin College Cambridge Bursary − £1.000	2009
Honors & Awards • British Computer Society Distinguished Dissertation Competition, nominated 20		
	• Eurographics Award for Best PhD Thesis, nominated – short-listed	2016
	• Eurographics Best Paper Award, 2nd prize	2014
	• Cyprus RIF <i>Students in Research</i> Competition, 1st prize – € 3.500	2010
	• Youth Board of Cyprus Postgraduate Award – € 1.700	2009
	• Cyprus RIF <i>Students in Research</i> Competition, 2nd prize – € 3.400	2009
	• Highest GPA in Univ. of Cyprus Computer Science Dept. (three awards) –	€3.400 2009
Teaching	University of Cyprus, Nicosia, Cyprus	
Experience	Department of Computer Science	
	Instructor for the following courses:	T. II 2022
	• MAI644 – Computer Vision (Master in AI)	Fall 2023
	DSC515 – Deep Learning	Fall 2022
	CS447 – Computer Vision	Spring 2021–2022
	CS653 – Computer Games Software Engineering	Spring 2016–2019
	Computer Games Summer School	Summer 2016
	CS607 – Visual Computing	Fall 2015
	CS032 – Programming Problem Solving Methods	Fall 2015
	University College London, London, UK	
	Department of Computer Science	
	Teaching Assistant for Image Processing (GV12) course	Fall 2012–2013

Supervision	PhD Students	
	Yeshwanth Kumar (CUT)	2021 – present
	Yiangos Georgiou (UCY)	2020 – present
	• Marios Loizou (UCY)	2018 – present
	MSc Students	
	Menghang Hao (UCL)	2022
	Yicheng Zhan (UCL)	2022
	• Jiamin Wang (UCL)	2021
	Maria Maslioukova (UCY - distinction)	2021
	• Kyriakos Zantis (UCY - distinction)	2019
	• Sergios Stamatis (UCY - distinction)	2018
	BSc Students	
	Andreas Mylidonis (UCY)	2021
	• Stephanos Kyriakides (UCY)	2018
	• Christos Othonos (UCY - distinction)	2017
	Interns	
	Tejas Anvekar	Year-round 2023-2024
	Nima Alizadeh	Summer 2022
	Andreas Kouzelis	Summer 2021
	Manos Papageorgiou	Summer 2020
	Pardis Ghaz	Year-round 2020
	Mona Hodaei	Year-round 2020
	• Elie El Hachem	Summer 2019

Professional

Program Committees

ACTIVITIES

Eurographics - Posters Chair	2024
CVPR Workshop on Structural and Compositional Learning on 3D Data	2023
Shape Modeling International	2018–202
International Symposium on Visual Computing	2018–2022
Computer Graphics International	2018–2019
WSCG Conference on Computer Graphics, Visualization and Computer Vision	2017
IEEE Melecon	2016
SIGGRAPH Asia Workshop on Creative Shape Modeling and Design	2014

Reviewer in International Journals

ACM Transactions on Graphics, Computer Graphics Forum, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, Computers and Graphics, Graphical Models, Computer Graphics and Applications, Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research, Knowledge-Based Systems

Reviewer in International Conferences

CVPR, ICCV, ECCV, SIGGRAPH, SIGGRAPH Asia, Eurographics, Pacific Graphics, Computer Graphics International, Shape Modeling International, International Symposium on Visual Computing

Administration

CYENS Centre of Excellence, Nicosia, Cyprus

DUTIES

- IT Infrastructure Committee Member 2023–present
- AI Cluster Committee Chair

2021-present

• Doctoral Training Program Committee - Chair

2020-2022

• Scientific Council - Member

2019-present

Journal Publications

- [1] Loizou, M., Garg, S., Petrov, D., **Averkiou, M.**, Kalogerakis, E. 2023. Cross-Shape Attention for Part Segmentation of 3D Point Clouds. *Computer Graphics Forum* 42, 5. (also presented in *SGP* 2023) (project website)
- [2] Artopoulos, G., Maslioukova, M.I., Zavou, C., Loizou, M., Deligiorgi, M., **Averkiou, M.** 2022. An Artificial Neural Network Framework for annotating and classifying Architectural Structure and Style of Built Heritage in 3D. *Journal of Cultural Heritage 63*, pp. 135–147 (project website)
- [3] Deligiorgi, M., Maslioukova, M.I., **Averkiou, M.**, Andreou, A.C., Selvaraju, P., Kalogerakis, E., Patow, G., Chrysanthou, Y. and Artopoulos, G., 2021. A 3D digitisation workflow for architecture-specific annotation of built heritage. *Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports*, 37, p.102787. (project website)
- [4] Loizou, M., **Averkiou, M.**, Kalogerakis, E. 2020. Learning Part Boundaries from 3D Point Clouds. *Computer Graphics Forum* 39, 5, pp. 183—195. (also presented in *SGP* 2020 acceptance rate: 36%) (project website)
- [5] Hu, R., Li, W., van Kaick, O., Huang, H., **Averkiou, M.**, Cohen-Or, D., Zhang, H. 2017. Co-Locating Style-Defining Elements on 3D Shapes. *ACM Transactions on Graphics 36*, 3, pp. 33:1–33:15. (also presented in *SIGGRAPH 2017* acceptance rate: 28%) (project website)
- [6] **Averkiou, M.**, Kim, V.G., Mitra, N.J. 2016. Autocorrelation Descriptor for Efficient Coalignment of 3D Shape Collections. *Computer Graphics Forum* 35, 1, pp. 261–271. (also presented in *Eurographics* 2016) (project website)
- [7] Fish, N.*, **Averkiou, M.***, van Kaick, O., Sorkine-Hornung, O., Cohen-Or, D., Mitra, N. J. 2014. Meta-representation of Shape Families. *ACM Transactions on Graphics* 33, 4, pp. 34:1-34:11. *joint first authors. (also presented in *SIGGRAPH* 2014 acceptance rate: 25%) (project website)
- [8] **Averkiou, M.**, Kim, V.G., Zheng, Y., Mitra, N.J. 2014. ShapeSynth: Parameterizing Model Collections for Coupled Shape Exploration and Synthesis. *Computer Graphics Forum* 33, 2, pp. 125-134. (also presented in *Eurographics* 2014 acceptance rate: 25%) (project website)
- [9] Zheng, Y., Cohen-Or, D., Averkiou, M., Mitra, N.J. 2014. Recurring Part Arrangements in Shape Collections. *Computer Graphics Forum 33*, 2, pp. 115-124. (also presented in *Eurographics*

Conference Publications

- [10] Petrov, D., Goyal, P., Thamizharasan, V., Kim, V., Gadelha, M., Averkiou, M., Chaudhuri, S., Kalogerakis, E. 2024. GEM3D: GEnerative Medial Abstractions for 3D Shape Synthesis. In *Proceedings of SIGGRAPH*. (project website)
- [11] Georgiou, Y., Loizou, M., Kelly, T., **Averkiou, M.** 2024. FacadeNet: Conditional Facade Synthesis via Selective Editing. In *Proceedings of Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)*, pp. 5384–5393. (project website)
- [12] Georgiou, Y., **Averkiou**, **M.**, Kelly, T. Kalogerakis, E. 2021. Projective Urban Texturing. In *Proceedings of International Conference on 3D Vision (3DV)*, pp. 1034–1043. (project website)
- [13] Selvaraju, P., Nabail, M., Loizou, M., Maslioukova, M., Averkiou, M., Andreou, A., Chaudhuri, S., Kalogerakis, E. 2021. BuildingNet: Learning to Label 3D Buildings. In *Proceedings of IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, pp. 10377–10387. **Oral Paper (acceptance rate for oral papers: 3%)** (project website)
- [14] Lin, H., **Averkiou**, M., Kalogerakis, E., Kovacs, B., Ranade, S., Kim, V. G., Chaudhuri, S., Bala, K. 2018. Learning Material-Aware Local Descriptors for 3D Shapes. In *Proceedings of International Conference on 3D Vision (3DV)*, pp. 150–159.
- [15] Kalogerakis, E., **Averkiou**, **M.**, Maji, S., Chaudhuri, S. 2017. 3D Shape Segmentation with Projective Convolutional Networks. In *Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, pp. 3779–3788. **Oral Paper (acceptance rate for oral papers: 2.65%)** (project website)
- [16] Zheng, S., Prisacariu, V. A., **Averkiou, M.**, Cheng, M. M., Mitra, N. J., Shotton, J., Torr, P.H.S., Rother, C. 2015. Object Proposals Estimation in Depth Image Using Compact 3D Shape Manifolds. In *Lecture Notes in Computer Science*, vol 9358 Proceedings of German Conference on Pattern Recognition (GCPR), pp. 196–208. (project website)
- [17] **Averkiou**, **M.**, Mitra, N.J. 2012. Automatic Alignment of Shape Collections. In *Proceedings of Eurographics* 2012 *Posters Track*.
- [18] **Averkiou, M.**, Dodgson, N. 2011. Comparison of relative (mouse-like) and absolute (tablet-like) interaction with a large stereoscopic work-space. In *Proceedings of the Stereoscopics Displays and Applications XXII Conference*.
- [19] **Averkiou, M.**, Chrysanthou, Y. 2009. Evaluating a multi-touch interface for 3D navigation inside the virtual world of a museum exhibit. In *Proceedings of the 10th VAST International Symposium on Virtual Reality, Archaeology and Cultural Heritage*.
- [20] Kunkel, T., **Averkiou, M.**, Chrysanthou, Y. 2008. A web-based virtual museum application. In *Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Virtual Systems and Multimedia*.

Working Papers & Preprints	[21] Adimoolam, Y. K., Chatterjee, B., Poullis, C., Averkiou , M. 2024. Pix2Poly: A Sequence Prediction Method for End-to-end Polygonal Building Footprint Extraction. (under review).
	[22] Adimoolam, Y. K., Chatterjee, B., Poullis, C., Averkiou, M. 2023. Efficient Deduplication and Leakage Detection in Large Scale Image Datasets with a focus on the CrowdAI Mapping Challenge Dataset. <i>arXiv preprint arXiv:2304.02296</i> (under review).
THESES & TECHNICAL REPORTS	[23] Averkiou, M. 2015. Data-driven Modelling of Shape Structure. University College London
	[24] Averkiou, M. 2010. 3D Interfaces for 3D Modelling. University of Cambridge
	[25] Averkiou, M. 2010. Digital Watermarking. University of Cambridge

of a museum exhibit. University of Cyprus

[26] Averkiou, M. 2009. A multi-touch interface for 3D navigation inside the virtual world